<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Passive obedience, stated and asserted In a sermon preached at Ampthill in Bedfordshire, upon Sunday, Septemb. 9. 1683. being the day of thanksgiving for the discovering and defeating the late treasonable conspiracy against His Sacred Majesities person and government. By Tho. Pomfret, A.M. rector of Ampthill, and chaplain to the Right Honourable Robert []ar, of Atlesbury.</title>
            <author>Pomfret, Thomas, d. 1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217677</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55347)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1977:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Passive obedience, stated and asserted In a sermon preached at Ampthill in Bedfordshire, upon Sunday, Septemb. 9. 1683. being the day of thanksgiving for the discovering and defeating the late treasonable conspiracy against His Sacred Majesities person and government. By Tho. Pomfret, A.M. rector of Ampthill, and chaplain to the Right Honourable Robert []ar, of Atlesbury.</title>
                  <author>Pomfret, Thomas, d. 1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], iii, [1], 31, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Joanna Brome, at the Gun in S. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Last three pages are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33769:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Paſſive Obedience, Stated and Aſſerted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN A SERMON PREACHED At <hi>Ampthill</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> Sunday, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 9. 1683.</p>
            <p>Being the Day of THANKSGIVING FOR THE Diſcovering and Defeating The Late Treaſonable CONSPIRACY AGAINST <hi>His Sacred Majeſties Perſon and Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>THO. POMFRET,</hi> A. M. Rector of <hi>Ampthill,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>ROBERT</hi> Ear. of <hi>Ailesbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Joanna Brome,</hi> at the Gun in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33769:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:33769:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable ROBERT Earl of</hi> Ailesbury, <hi>One of the Lords of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy-Council.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COuld I have taken the Confidence to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted your Commands, this Diſcourſe would not have needed that Protection, and Favour, which now it humbly begs. Not but that I am well aſſured, the Doctrines in it are truly Chriſtian, but it is ſent forth into an ill natur'd, and Plotting Age, that will not give tolerable entertainment to any Principles but ſuch as invite to Apoſtacy, and Rebellion. It is not therefore without extream Neceſſity, that I preſs to Your Lordſhip, in this Dedication; the very aſſerting Primitive Religion, and Chriſtian Loyalty, will need ſuch a Patron. And though it is no Secret to the World, yet I cannot forbear declaring that I
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:33769:3"/>
cannot have ſuch a Defender as Your Self, who does ſo generouſly practiſe both thoſe Vertues. I have ſeen in Your Lordſhip ſuch Concernment for the Crown, and the Eſtabliſh'd Religion, that I might preſume of Patronage; But I muſt beſeech Your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don too, that I preſent this, (of which I have ſo mean an Opinion my ſelf) to a Perſon for whom of all men, I have the greateſt Honour, and from whom I have received the greateſt Obligations. But You loved the Subject, and therefore liked the Sermon, no Man ever having better joyned the Chriſtian and the Statesman. And truly (my Lord) I have been entertained with the greateſt Delight as well as Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, in Your own Diſcourſes of Loyalty, <hi>that</hi> it ſelf in You being founded upon Principles truly Noble and Brave; not living upon future Expectances, but ſerving Your Prince, as You do Your God, by the Engagements of pure Love, and undeſigning Vertue: And therefore in all Changes You was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Your Self, no Change of State making You change Your Party. This is removed as far from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth, as it is from Flattery, that You can no more forſake Your King nor Your Religion, that You
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:33769:3"/>
can Your Self, being one that values not Your Fortune, nor Your Greatneſs, above Your Vertues. And as to this, all men that know You will allow the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, ſo it is my happineſs, as well as intereſt, that I can teſtifie it by a daily Experience,
having the honour of being</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and obedient Chaplain,</hi> Tho. Pomfret.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:33769:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33769:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON <bibl>I<hi> S.</hi> PET. ii. 20, 21.</bibl>

               <q>But if when ye do well, and ſuffer for it, ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God. For even hereunto were ye called.</q>
            </head>
            <p>IT is not unknown to any man who has heard the Sermons, or read the Books, or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the Practices of all ſorts of Diſſenters from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but that they have been a People not only the moſt ungovernable, but alſo the moſt deſtructive to the Peace, and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Lives of Princes. It cannot therefore be any thing ſtrange, to hear by the King's <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> of a Conſpiracy complotted againſt His <hi>own</hi> Life and Government, ſince it is by ſuch, whoſe very Principles do ſo naturally tend to Sedition, and Bloud. And tho' indeed by God's wonderful Providence, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath been hitherto deliver'd from the Malicious, Unchriſtian,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33769:5"/>
and cruel Deſigns of theſe men; yet I cannot ſee, without a continuation of Miracles, how it is poſſible for our Government and Religion, to be render'd in any degree ſafe, unleſs ſuch <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> be rooted out, and renounced, which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lead to diſturb and ruin Kingdoms. For ſince the Supreme Power, is both by Gods expreſs Order, and the conſent of all Nations, abſolute and unaccountable; if you once take the Sword out of the Magiſtrate's hand, and put it into the Peoples, that Nation is preſently in a ſtate of War, and every man may thruſt his dagger into his Neighbours ſide, if he has a ſtronger Arm, and a more bloudy mind. To prevent this; by Gods Ordinance, and the agreement of all Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, the Supreme Power <hi>only</hi> is to bear the Sword, and <hi>that</hi> to defend every mans Right, but no man to riſe up, <hi>upon any Pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi> againſt <hi>that.</hi> A concluſion this, that is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God and Nature, Reaſon and Religion, and has been conſented to by all good Chriſtians, and wiſer Heathens.</p>
            <p>But ſome hot and troubleſome men amongſt us, given up to Rage and Ambition, have torn up the Foundations of Peace and Government, and will endure neither Kings, nor their Laws; but hate their Power, and would violate their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to bring in their own Devices, and inlarge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33769:5"/>
their Grandeurs. Nay, and that Chriſtianity it ſelf, which is the greateſt obligation in all the World, to Peace and Obedience, might have no effect towards the preſervation of Gods <hi>Vice-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> they will make the Chriſtian Religion, the pretence to Rebellion, and for the concernments of God, practiſe directly oppoſite to all his Commandments<hi>:</hi> and amongſt the reſt, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently againſt this of the Text, where we are injoyn'd to ſuffer, though it be for doing well. <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> which is a patient and mild ſuffering the hard, and unjuſt uſages of Kings, being both the Chriſtians duty, and profeſſion; that at once he might poſſeſs his mind in patience, and ſecure the Publick Quiet.</p>
            <p>But this meek and Chriſtian Principle, was of late called to an account; and by Arguments of railery and contempt, indeavoured to be hooted out of the World; and repreſented to be mean and baſe, tamely to ſuffer evil, and far more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to be inroll'd amongſt the <hi>Banditi,</hi> and <hi>Ruſſians,</hi> than in the Catalogue of <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly to give the more confidence to their horrid plot, the <hi>Chaplain,</hi> and the <hi>Goliah</hi> of the Conſpiracy was ſent forth to bid defyance, to God, and the King, and the whole Army of Martyrs; and to tell the World, that his Maſters were men of that mettle, that with his own
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33769:6"/>
               <hi>Julian,</hi> they would turn Apoſtates to all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and rather than ſuffer as Chriſtians, confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in Treaſon. Upon this principle their wicked Deſign proceeded, and therefore it is but needful that it be conſider'd, and for the future (if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) prevented: which I ſhall endeavour from the Text; where we have a paſſive Obedience commended; God's acceptation of it; and our own calling to it. Which I ſhall render more plain in theſe following Propoſitions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>That as Chriſtians, we are bound to do well, though we ſuffer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>When we do well, and ſuffer for it, we muſt take it patiently.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>If we do well, and according to the Chriſtian Rule, we will rather ſuffer patiently than reſiſt the power by which we ſuffer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>That as all theſe are acceptable to God, ſo to them all, we are call'd by our Religion: it is both the duty, and end of our Chriſtian Vocation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I. <hi>That we muſt do well, though we ſuffer for it.</hi> And indeed having this Conſcience, that we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33769:6"/>
do well, it will be eaſie to ſuffer the utmoſt that we fear, or the worſt that men threaten: keep the Conſcience but clear of guilt, and the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing though it bring ſmart, can do us no miſchief. Only here, both the Prudence and Innocence, of a Chriſtian does require, that we bring not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering upon our ſelves for evil doing. A caution S. <hi>Peter,</hi> thought neceſſary, that the ſufferings of his time might be truly Chriſtian. 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> iv. 15. <hi>But let none of you ſuffer as a Murderer, or as a Thief, or as an Evil-doer, or as a Buſy-body in other mens matters.</hi> All Evils as they have their proper and legal Remedies, ſo too there are peculiar, and diſtinct Phyſicians. The maladies of the State, and the corruptions of the Church, muſt be purg'd by the Governours of both: and though private Subjects may condole the miſcarriages in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or innovations in Religion, yet they muſt not without due Power and legal Authority, turn State-menders and Church-reformers. Many things may be neceſſary, and well done if accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd by due means: ſo that we are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not only the goodneſs or neceſſity of the thing, but alſo what we have to do in it. For St. <hi>Peter</hi> you ſee ranks the <hi>Buſy-body,</hi> with very ill Companions, <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Murderers;</hi> enough one would think to reſtrain all People, from mending what they are not concern'd in; and to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33769:7"/>
aſſure them, that if they ſuffer as <hi>Buſy-bodies,</hi> it is ſo far from dying as Chriſtians, that it is with ſhame and diſgrace, it being the Cauſe, not the Death, that gives both the Martyrdom, and the Honour. Hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his own juſtification, when he was Accuſed of the <hi>Jews,</hi> told <hi>Felix,</hi> that <hi>they neither found him with multitudes, nor with tumult,</hi> Act. xxiv. 18. and challenges his Accuſers at <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>if they could find any evil-doing in him.</hi> He had done nothing againſt their Laws nor Government, he heads no Faction, nor is concern'd in any Conſults for the deſtruction of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and by theſe things he teſtifies his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Innocence. No man ought, to think, that he ſuffers with honour, who is ſo far from ſuffering for <hi>doing well,</hi> that he does an <hi>Evil</hi> to prevent that which he fears to ſuffer. The caſe <hi>this,</hi> of all Plotters againſt Government; they fear, or at leaſt pretend ſome Evil to their Perſons and Eſtates, from the unlimited Power of the Prince, and then againſt the Laws both of God and Man, conſpire his ruin. And can theſe men be allowed to ſuffer for doing well; who dye as Criminals to the Laws both of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth?</hi> the Law of God requiring that no ill Action be done to prevent the greateſt Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; and the Laws of Men condemning them as Tranſgreſſors, for doing ill. And in the mean
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33769:7"/>
time, Chriſtian meekneſs is loſt too, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us; though we do well, and yet ſuffer, to take it patiently: which is my Second Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>II. <hi>When we do well, and ſuffer for it, we muſt take it patiently.</hi> Patience it is, that makes our ſuffering eaſie; that fanns us with ſweet and pleaſant gales, when the fires are about us; that rocks us aſleep in the midſt of torments<hi>:</hi> our own impatience being the greateſt trouble; both aggravating the other, and afflicting more ſharply by it ſelf. It was Chriſt's command to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and in them to all Chriſtians, ſpeaking to them about the Perſecutions of the laſt times, S. <hi>Luke,</hi> xxi. 19. <hi>In Patience poſſeſs ye your Souls.</hi> He foretold 'em what they ſhould expect, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. and ſo onward, <hi>to be perſecuted, to be deliver'd up to the Synagogues, impriſon'd, and betrayed by Kindred, by Parents, by Brethren, to be put to death, and hated of all men for his ſake:</hi> yet for all that, <hi>in Patience poſſeſs ye your Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to ſuffer patiently, is firſt, to be content with what we ſuffer: and if once thus we were, our murmuring would ceaſe, our grudgings were at an end; we would not <hi>revile God's High-Prieſt, nor ſpeak evil of the Ruler of his People:</hi> much leſs, combine to remove thoſe Princes whom our own Fret and Malice, and Ambition, only
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33769:8"/>
make uneaſie. We would not ſtumble at ſtraws; nor no mountains caſt upon us would unſettle us, would ſhake our Loyalty; ſuch is the Power, and vertue of a contented patience.</p>
            <p>Yet that's not all. He is content with his Fortune that neither repines nor murmurs at it; this may be Heathen patience, but it is not Chriſtian. That man only is Chriſtianly patient, that ſecondly, is chearful in it; does not only quietly and ſerenely ſuffer wrong, but rejoyces in it. This, the true Martyrs patience; ſuch as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the firſt Chriſtians, who took joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods, knowing that in Heaven they had a more induring ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>This cheerfulneſs ſometimes works to a Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſometimes ariſes from it; however a full Reſignation of our ſelves into the hands of God, is always a companion of, and a neceſſary ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and muſt be the third in Chriſtian Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. He ſuffers patiently, that ſuffers without reluctance, that is ſo at the diſpoſe of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that he has not ſo much as a deſire, or wiſh within him, for any thing concerning his tribulation, or iſſue of it, but what it pleaſes God to make him; who is content to live in torment, or die in pain, or change his condition as often, and as many ways as it ſhall ſeem beſt to the wiſdome of his Heavenly Father: this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33769:8"/>
is perfect Patience, and this is patiently to ſuffer as Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>There are who would be counted ſuch; whom yet every thing diſturbs, whom every little ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcontents, who are always repining at ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Powers, who upon every petty grievance, ſpeak evil of Authority, whoſe haſty deſires never wait God's leiſure, but ſeek out ſpeedy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Remedies to themſelves; and yet will needs be counted patient men, the only Martyrs. But call we this Patience to Rage againſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Nay, and when we are juſtly ſentenced for our faults, even then to ſuffer with reviling mouths, and ſeditious ſpeeches! neither to truſt our Deliverance to God's Providence, nor our ſafety to the Laws! not only to preſcribe to God, means, and time, to help them; but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire by the moſt diſhonourable, as well as the moſt wicked ways to free themſelves, from ſuch miſchiefs which only their own folly and malice have created to themſelves! Plotting thus againſt their own Peace, by needleſs jealouſies, and then make that very jealouſie, a ſufficient ground to contrive the King's ruin! Certainly, theſe men, have other principles than what Chriſt left them; who being reviled, reviled not again, who when he ſuffered, threatned not, but committed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to him that judgeth righteouſly; who yet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33769:9"/>
had full power to have judg'd them himſelf: only that he might leave us an Example, how to behave our ſelves when men oppreſs us, to be content when men oppreſs us, to be content with it, chearful under it, and refer the reſt to God. And this will make way for my third Propoſition:</p>
            <p>III. <hi>If we do well, we will rather ſuffer pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, than take revenge upon, or reſiſt the Power which God has ſet over us.</hi> If the Authority be juſt, Obedience is neceſſary; not always to do what is commanded, for it may be Evil; and then God muſt be obey'd, not man<hi>:</hi> yet to man, ſo much Obedience, even in that, is due, as to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit patiently to the penalty is inflicted on us, though it be unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Indeed naturally, every man has a Right of Reſiſtance, to repell an Injury from himſelf: yet this his private power, for peace and quiet ſake, is reſtrain'd with bounds by that Superiors power under which he is. So that being a Member of a Common-wealth, or Kingdom, he has no Reſiſtance lawfull, permitted to him, but what is indulged or commanded to him by the Law under which he lives; which certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies him any reſiſtance of the ſupreme Power it it ſelf, be it what it will; elſe were there no way left to quiet any time the Seditious, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33769:9"/>
the publick peace, neither could the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the ſupreme Authority be defended, were there left to the Subjects a liberty to gainſay, or withſtand, much leſs to reſiſt it: whence it comes, that there are ſo many cautelous, and even ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Laws, invented by <hi>Parliament,</hi> to keep the Perſon, and Power, and Dignity, of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour Sacred and Inviolable.</p>
            <p>Therefore as to that pretence, that by nature we have a freedome to withſtand force, by force, and may deliver our ſelves by the deſtruction of that Power which would inſlave us; it is to be conſider'd. That in all eſtabliſh'd Governments the People have deveſted themſelves from the rights and practices of thoſe Liberties, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which otherwiſe they might make, and enjoy. For becauſe it was ſoon found out that every ſingle man would be a Prey to any other that was ſtronger than himſelf, therefore all people thought it neceſſary to combine themſelves into Societies, and unite their Strength by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it all into the hand of one man, who ſhould defend all the reſt. Now the <hi>Concluſion</hi> from hence is; if the power of defending, and revenging of wrongs, be committed by the People, to one Man, for the ends of Government, then this Power is given from themſelves, and ſtated in the Supreme, there to remain. The ſame natural
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33769:10"/>
reaſon that makes Government neceſſary, making it as neceſſary that the Governour be obeyed: but then he cannot be judg'd, nor he moſt not be reſiſted; for the Supreme cannot be both above and under the People: but it is ſo, if the People can avenge their own wrongs; for that which avenges muſt alſo be ſupreme; which becauſe in no Monarchy the People are, therefore they muſt be quiet, and patient; for how can they right themſelves againſt him whom they cannot call to judgement?</p>
            <p>The very Heathens ſaw this neceſſary ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without any other light than what Nature gave them. <hi>Principi ſummum imperium Dii dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ſubditis obſequia gloria relicta eſt,</hi> ſays <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> The divine Power has given the ſupreme Arbitrament of all things to the Prince, the only glory left to Subjects is Obedience. <hi>Aequum at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iniquum Regis imperium feras.</hi> Seneca. The Kings Command, be it juſt or unjuſt, muſt be ſuffer'd. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is all the reaſon <hi>Euripides</hi> gave in this caſe, Governours they are, and therefore muſt be obeyed.</p>
            <p>Nor was Paſſive Obedience due only to the ſupreme Magiſtrate, but to all the reſt proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, to inferiour Governours, to Fathers, and Maſters. It was <hi>Roman</hi> Law, <hi>Miles qui caſtigare volenti Centurioni reſiſterit, ſi vitem tenuit, militiam</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33769:10"/>
               <hi>mutat, ſi ex induſtria fregit, velmanum Centurioni in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit, capite punitur.</hi> That Souldier which reſiſts his Captain when he comes to beat him for his faults, if he lay hold upon his Commander's Cudgel, ſhall be preſently diſcarded, but if he break it, or lay hold upon him, he ſhall die for it. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> though he ſpoke not Law, ſpoke the ground of it, when he ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; If a Magiſtrate ſtrike us, we muſt not ſtrike again. And <hi>Cicero</hi> for our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſays the ſame: <hi>Non modo reticere homines parentum injurias, ſed etiam aequo animo ferre oportet,</hi> We muſt bear our Parents injuries with ſilence and patience; ſo natural Piety does enjoin us: Servants were bound to a more ſtrict obedience to their Maſters by the Civil-Laws, which are nothing elſe but Concluſions deduced from the Principles of Natural Reaſon, and are in this, back'd by the Judicial. Thus even Nature taught them, which yet makes all equal, but however born to be obedient to the ſtate, wherein they are to be.</p>
            <p>And all this is but reaſon, for the inferiour having either by voluntary Choice as <hi>Servants,</hi> or by Natural deſcent as <hi>Children,</hi> or by condition of ſtate or ſucceſſion as <hi>Subjects,</hi> given up their right of all, and the diſpoſe of themſelves to the wiſdome and diſcretion of their Governors,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33769:11"/>
have no reaſon to reſiſt their Commands and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, becauſe in ſo doing they contradict themſelves<hi>:</hi> firſt willing and deſiring one thing in their ſupreme Governour, (who is vertually each of them) and then the contrary by a new affection of their own.</p>
            <p>'Tis requiſite therefore that one of theſe be repeal'd, the firſt is not now in our power to do, 'tis out of our hand, without a limitation. The ſecond therefore we muſt correct, either by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to what the other ſhall think juſt, or by ſuffering for tranſgreſſing it, when we cannot do it with a ſafe and quiet Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Yet in all this, with St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s order, <hi>Si aliquid juſſerit Curator, faciendum, non tamen ſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Proconſul jubeat; aut ſi Conſul aliquid jubeat, &amp; aliud Imperator, non utique contemnis poteſtatem, ſed eligis majori ſervire:</hi> If an inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate command, we muſt Obey; yet if the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour injoyn the contrary, we muſt ſuffer the inferiour's violence againſt us; but do what the ſuperiour bids us.</p>
            <p>But I leave Nature and Reaſon, becauſe men have forgot them, and I might upon the ſame account omit <hi>Scripture</hi> alſo, but it is the Word of <hi>Eternal Truth,</hi> and we muſt not ſlightly paſs over it. And in it how read we? In the Old Teſtament, at the firſt inſtitution of Kings,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33769:11"/>
1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 11. when he had told them <hi>how their King ſhould uſe them, uſurp upon their Land and Vineyards, and Wives and Children, and take of them what he pleaſed,</hi> What then? ſhall they lift up themſelves, and ſtir againſt him? No, <hi>ye ſhall cry out in that day for the King which ye have choſen you.</hi> verſ. 18.</p>
            <p>There is all the remedy you have in caſe of his Tyranny and Oppreſſion, to cry out in that day unto the Lord. And it is ſtrange if any Licenſe of Reſiſtance was ever granted by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, that in a People ſo obſtinate, ſo ready to perverſeneſs, as the <hi>Jews,</hi> we never read of any Party that roſe up againſt their Kings, (though wicked and ungodly) to vindicate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their unjuſt Grievances; which muſt needs ariſe by the Idolatry of ſuch who Rul'd over them; unleſs ſuch who were peculiarly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriz'd from Heaven, or ſuch whoſe Actions are Recorded for Hiſtory, and Teſtimony of God's Providence in ſuffering them, not of his Teſtimony in approving them.</p>
            <p>Nay more; the very Idols of the Heathens, how grievous ſoever to the devout and pious Souls, were not demoliſh'd by any private hand, they were fain to ſuffer it, it being not juſtly in their power to do otherwiſe. And you may read of the indiſcreet Zeal of a Chriſtian Biſhop
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33769:12"/>
who againſt the Emperours Command or Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, throwing down an Idols Temple, was the occaſion of a violent perſecution. God is a God of Order, and would have none go beyond their bounds, but do their duty, and commit the reſt to his wiſer diſpoſal.</p>
            <p>But however not to reſiſt, for that of all the reſt is incompatible with Suffering, <hi>You muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needs be ſubject,</hi> Rom. xiii. 5. For to ſay no more, <hi>whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> It is in vain to ſay more, being ſo plain to any man to underſtand, that ſeriouſly thinks of a Day of Judgment; when all the dawbing of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> ſhall be wiped off, and no pretence nor diſtinction ſatisfie againſt the Evidence of Truth, and ſo plain expreſſions.</p>
            <p>And if you pleaſe to have any more of God's mind, you ſhall ſee in <hi>Scripture,</hi> that He is ſo tender of Kings, that not only they ſhall not be ill uſed, but not ſo much as ill thought, or ſpoke of, <hi>Eccl.</hi> x. 10. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought.</hi> Nay, and to prevent all Rebellion from ſhrouding it ſelf under the new invented terms of <hi>Heats</hi> and <hi>Stirs,</hi> God himſelf has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>Prov.</hi> xxx. 31. <hi>Where the word of a King is there is power, and who can ſay unto him</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33769:12"/>
               <hi>What doeſt thou? Againſt him there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This perhaps all men will agree to, but when the Prince is evil, and does wrong, invades Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and intrenches upon Liberty, or indangers our Religion. For what then? Why the Rule in Scripture relates to ſuch Princes that are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be Evil; for no man will Curſe him whom he thinks to be good and gracious; but be he never ſo Evil, Curſe him not, no not in thy Mind, much leſs with thy Tongue, and then to be ſure to do him no harm with thy Hand, when thou muſt not ſo much as intend, or wiſh it in thy Thought. <hi>Reſiſt not Evil</hi> is our Saviour's injunction, <hi>Mat.</hi> v. 39. we muſt hurt no man, nay not that man from whom we receive hurt; for no man muſt be his own Avenger. If a private hand does me an Injury, I have no way to defend my ſelf, but by the Magiſtrate and by the Law. But then if my Prince does me Evil, how ſhall I render Evil back to him? It muſt be by ſome Power ſuperiour to his, but that is none but Gods. Here therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Rule comes in, <hi>Rom.</hi> xii. 37. <hi>Not to render Evil for Evil, but to give place to wrath,</hi> that is, to the Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Evil Princes are to be referred to that; and to this agree our Laws, declaring, That the King <hi>receives his Power only from Gods hand,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33769:13"/>
               <hi>and therefore he is accountable only at His Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well; but then the People are but in an ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condition: for if Kings who are for our defence ſhall turn Wolves, and deſtroy us; inſtead of being Nurſing-Fathers, ſhall eat up their Children; if againſt Law, they ſhall impoſe upon our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and our Conſciences, and not allow a legal freedom in our Eſtates, and Religion, what then? why! the queſtion ſtill is, whether they be Kings, or not? For if they be ſupreme, we cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, nor correct what is above us. Our preſent remedy is Patience, and we muſt leave all the reſt to God's Care and Puniſhment; for we our ſelves are tyed up, and we muſt not reſiſt.</p>
            <p>And ſay, there is any Caſe in which we might; what Caſe is that? I hope we ſhall not admit it in all; but then if you admit but one, that will be as bad, for ſeditious People will be ſure their Caſe ſhall be that. And if in any caſe at all, it muſt be certainly in the Caſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and here indeed all our Rebells croud in. Ay, but the <hi>Scriptures</hi> which teach our Religion, will not allow it in that Caſe neither: For even then, when the Emperours perſecuted Chriſtianity, and lived upon Blood, and ſatisfied both their Malice and their Pleaſure in the death of Chriſtians: Yet ſtill ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ye muſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33769:13"/>
be ſubject, and ye muſt not reſiſt, for that will be your damnation; and you had better dye <hi>Martyrs</hi> than <hi>Rebells.</hi> Upon this reaſon the Chriſtians always laid down their weapons, and lifted up their hands in Prayer, threw away their Swords and took up the Croſs, and fought for no Crowns but thoſe of Martyrdom.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtill, we hope we may be concerned for the <hi>Publick,</hi> not that we have any private quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels againſt the King, or particular deſigns to make our ſelves great; but however as <hi>Patriots</hi> of the People, and <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of our Countrey, we muſt prevent miſchief, and not ſuffer the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth to be deſtroyed: and therefore it may be more adviſeable to cut off a dangerous Prince, than leave it in his election and power to deſtroy <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> By this ſpecious pretence it is, that our <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> cover, and defend their malicious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes<hi>:</hi> not remembring the Chriſtian Rule given by St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> iii. 8. <hi>Not to do Evil that Good may come of it.</hi> Thoſe miſchiefs which we fear hereafter, if they cannot lawfully be diverted, muſt be entertain'd whenever they ſhall happen, with patience and ſubmiſſion: and, as in that, there is more Chriſtianity, ſo too more Prudence, and a nobler Courage; for thus we preſerve the preſent Peace, leave future things to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33769:14"/>
of <hi>Providence,</hi> and our own preſervation, to the <hi>Laws</hi> and an harmleſs <hi>Innocence.</hi> We have a ſort of hot-headed Republicans, reprobating the Rights of the King, and the nobleſt Subject, by a kind of <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>irreſpective</hi> Decree, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Religion, Common-juſtice, and the Laws; not conſidering in the leaſt, the fatal conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and horrid injuſtice; ſo they can but wreck their malice upon the beſt of Kings, and the moſt generous of Brothers<hi>!</hi> But <hi>allowing</hi> thoſe things by which they would blacken them; are we to preſerve <hi>that</hi> which they call <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> (a compoſition of ſo many, that in the whole maſs it is none at all) againſt all the Rules we are to take from our common Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, as well as natural Juſtice? <hi>Not to do Evil that Good may come of it,</hi> is the direction of our <hi>Bible;</hi> not to put that upon another which we would not endure that others ſhould put upon us, is the Rule of <hi>Equity;</hi> and not to ſet the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into a preſent flame, for fear heareafter a tempeſtuous Prince ſhould Govern it, is I preſume, a concluſion from <hi>Policy.</hi> And though <hi>Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> be a very dear Principle, yet certainly not to be perſued by the violation of thoſe Rights that are eſtabli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h'd by Divine and Humane Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33769:14"/>
Theſe are the things that we have ſo long, and ſo juſtly complain'd of in the <hi>Tenets</hi> and <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of our Adverſaries of <hi>Rome:</hi> but whilſt we thus fear, and ſtrive, and cry out againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> ſhall we our ſelves maintain one of the ſaddeſt points of it; in our Affronting, Oppoſing, and Conſpiring againſt Kings? glorying ſo long in the <hi>Word</hi> Proteſtant, till we altogether diſclaim the Chriſtian; and by a pretence of Zeal againſt one Religion, become a ſcandal, and a ſhame to all! For as to Government you cannot tell me which is worſt, the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> or the <hi>Diſſenter:</hi> for if the King be inferiour to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> or to the <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> as the other do affirm; it is but charging him with miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors in Government, and then ſetting up the <hi>Paſtoral-Staff</hi> of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or the <hi>Standard</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and you may call him to an account with <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Blunderbuſs,</hi> and yet be Innocent. Thus the Scepter of the Prince, be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under the Keys of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or the Kirk of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> ſhall be Depos'd by every proud <hi>Prieſt</hi> or pragmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Presbyter;</hi> and it will be all one to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy which prevails, the Pope or the Faction. Nor is it any great matter what our People call themſelves, or of what Church they are; for I am ſure if they be Rebels, they cannot be good Chriſtians. Therefore I was always of Opinion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33769:15"/>
that thoſe men who can think it lawful to fight againſt their Prince, were the rankeſt Hypocrites in their pretences to Religion: for ſuch whoſe Conſciences are Armour of proof againſt the plain demonſtration of duty, will ſtick at no other ſin, when their Ambition or Intereſt, invites them to it. I have therefore continually wonder'd how ſuch, as might eaſily be obſerved both to ſpeak and practiſe ill things againſt the Government, could ever be thought to be Sober, and Pious People<hi>:</hi> remembring that when St. <hi>Jude</hi> was giving an account of baſe and wicked men, as a part of their Character tells us, they <hi>deſpiſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and ſpeaks evil of Dignities;</hi> which as he makes the mark of a prophane and wicked perſon, ſo the Apoſtle aggravates it, by obſerving that it is an uſing the Prince worſe than St. <hi>Michael</hi> would the <hi>Devil, againſt whom he brought no railing accuſation.</hi> To which meek and Chriſtian temper we ſhall the ſooner be perſuaded by conſidering the laſt Propoſition.</p>
            <p>IV. <hi>That to do well, and ſuffer patiently, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon us, by the Religion we profeſs.</hi> To this we are call'd, to do well, and yet ſuffer, to do well though we ſuffer, to ſuffer patiently, nay and to chooſe to ſuffer, rather than reſiſt, or riſe up.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33769:15"/>
It is Cowardiſe, not Chriſtianity to deſiſt from doing well, for fear of ſuffering evil; nor are dangers or undoing, or death it ſelf, Pleas ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to excuſe us from the performance of what is juſt and good<hi>:</hi> for this, ſays S. <hi>Peter,</hi> is <hi>the will of God, that with well-doing ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> verſ. 15, 16. <hi>as free, but not uſing your liberty as a cloak of maliciouſneſs but as the Servants of God;</hi> that is, as thoſe who are called to imitate the Patience of a Crucified Lord and Maſter. Chriſt gave his Diſciples the exacteſt Rule of Patience, ſay the Ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> not only, not to reſiſt, but not to ſeem to go about it; and from this place in the Text, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. 13, 14, 15, 16. of the Fourth Chapter they gather it, and to Chriſts Example they conform it; whoſe Example is propounded to us in the following verſes; who exalted alſo every vertue, and therefore this of Patience and Obedience, to their juſt perfection, and ſo enjoyns it to his Diſciples. This made the Chriſtian Church grow up to its height and ſplendour; for it was not the Sword of Fighting Men, but the Bloud of Patient Chriſtians, that ſpread the Name of Chriſt, and ſo gloriouſly defended it; it being the Chriſtians Principle to Suffer for his Name, not fight for it, but to be ſure rather to Suffer, than Rebell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33769:16"/>
And if you ask the firſt times of Chriſtianity, both their Actions and Words expreſs as much. The <hi>Thebaean</hi> Legion conſiſting of near <hi>Seven Thouſand</hi> Chriſtians, when the Emperour <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian,</hi> under pain of death, commanded them to Sacrifice to Idols, what did they? they ſtood not upon their guard, though they could eaſily have done it, but ſuffered themſelves to be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by the hands of ſome few Executioners ſent on purpoſe, and after that they threw down their weapons, and ſubmitted their Necks and unarmed Bodies, to the Sword of the Tyrant. <hi>Hoc ſolum reminiſcentes,</hi> (ſays the Story) <hi>ſe illum confiteri, qui nec reclamando ad occiſionem ductus eſt,</hi> only remembring this, that they confeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be his Diſciples, <hi>who was led like a Lamb dumb before his ſhearers, who did not open his mouth.</hi> And we read of as great a number un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Valens</hi> the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperour, who without any reſiſtance, ſubmitted themſelves to his Fury and Violence.</p>
            <p>Nor was it as the Author of <hi>Julian</hi> pretends (though againſt all the faith of Hiſtory) that in theſe Examples there wanted power of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; and <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells the Emperour as much, <hi>Externi ſumus, &amp; veſtra omnia implevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c. cui bello non idonei, non prompti fuiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, etiam copiis impares; qui tam libenter truci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damur,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33769:16"/>
               <hi>ſi non apud iſtam diſciplinam, magis occidi liciret, quam occidere.</hi> What Armies (ſays he) were we not ſufficient to grapple with, though we were fewer, who are yet ſo willingly ſlain, if by our Religion it were not more lawful to ſuffer, and be kill'd, rather than to kill others, by defending our ſelves. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays as much: and <hi>Lactantius</hi> thus expreſſes Patience: <hi>Ideo cum tam nefanda perpetimur, ne verbo quidem relucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ſed Deo remittimus ultionem.</hi> When we ſuffer ſuch horrible things, we do not ſo much as reſiſt them in words, but commit the revenge only to God. Thus they choſe to ſuffer, and thought themſelves called thereunto by their Religion.</p>
            <p>And if we would be truly Chriſtians, this muſt be our temper, this our practice. And I hope in what concerns our duty, whether to God, or Man, we ſhall take our meaſures from Chriſt, and primitive Religion, and not from ſuch hot and rebellious Zealots, who with God in their mouths will violate all that is ſacred and juſt, in their actions.</p>
            <p>I would only ſay one thing more. Here is an horrible Plot diſcovered, againſt the Life of the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>His Royal Highneſs:</hi> and this calls upon us all who have but an ordinary kindneſs, and reſpect to His Majeſty and the Government, for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33769:17"/>
two duties: The <hi>Firſt</hi> is, to pay unto God, an hearty Acknowledgment for his tender and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Providence over the King, and indeed in him, over us all, ſince in his Preſervation, we injoy our Lives, and Eſtates, our Liberties, and Religion. The other duty is, to ſet a mark upon thoſe Men, and ſuch Principles, which would have murdered the beſt of Kings, and the moſt Loyal part of the Nation, under a pretence of defending <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant-Religion.</hi> How far this wretched Plot it ſelf, is believed, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believed to be the Plot of thoſe Men againſt whom it is both Charged, and Proved, I cannot ſay; but this I will ſay, that the Practice of what they would have done, is ſo like, what by their Preachers they are taught to do, that if we do but conſider by whom the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are led, it is no wonder at all to find them ſo ready to do miſchief.</p>
            <p>And as I was ſaying at firſt, that their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples do ſo naturally tend to Rebellion, that they can never be made good Subjects, but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing their Maſters, and their Doctrines; So I now add, that if there be any one of them that is kind to the Government, it is the goodneſs more of his Nature than Perſuaſion, if they do believe their own Guides. I ſhall inſtance but in a few, but thoſe few, ſuch as were notoriouſly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33769:17"/>
active in the deſtruction of the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> and have been Teachers of the People in Conventicles ſince the Return of his preſent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> in a Speech at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> upon the calling in of the <hi>Scots</hi> to aſſiſt the Rebellion, to encourage ſo Pious a Cauſe, did aſſure his <hi>Auditors,</hi> that had he himſelf as many Lives as Hairs upon his Head, he would Sacrifice all in that Quarrel. A bleſſed Preſident for a factious People! Nay, and as to that very <hi>Principle</hi> upon which this wicked Plot was grounded, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the pretence of preſerving <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> he delivers his Opinion, That for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> it is commendable to Fight againſt the King's Command. <hi>Pag.</hi> 29. <hi>Theſes.</hi> The <hi>Pope</hi> in his Chair could not have determin'd more magiſterially, nor to more miſchievous purpoſes: And indeed the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by the ſame meaſures; for to gain the People to Fight againſt their Prince, they will at any time make over to them, the Sovereignty: And then as Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> aſſerts, all Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects (as now it is pretended) are the betrayers of Religion, and Liberty; and thoſe (ſays he) that fought under the King's Banner, did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by all bloudy and traiterous ways, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Religion and Property. So that here is Treaſon found in the King, againſt his Sovereign
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33769:18"/>
Lord the People! Therefore he declares the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion to be ſo much God's Cauſe, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever dyed in it, would dye a Martyr. <hi>Sermon to the Peers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> another of the ſame holy ſtamp, after the War which he had Preach'd up, was ended, and he had leiſure to calculate the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, both of Men and Money, conſumed upon that fatal occaſion, and had alſo weighed the King's Bloud, and all his Subjects that had been Murder'd, againſt the <hi>Covenant,</hi> he ſets down his Opinion at the foot of the Account, that the removal of the King, and Biſhops, was a ſufficient payment for all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oin and Treaſure that had been ſpent in thoſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>traction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; So that, it is no wonder at all, that, theſe men value not the bloud of Kings, nor their People; <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant-Religion,</hi> will anſwer for it all. And for that, you ſhall hear Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> too, (who has ſtill the guidance of Conſciences, and is Maſter of a Conventicle) declaring, That where Religion and Liberty, are the queſtion, it is not to be queſtion'd at all, but that the King, and all that adhere to him may be murder'd. Upon this account perhaps, he declares to the whole World by way of boaſt, that he had Preached Thouſands into the War, and that his own being ingaged in it, was the greateſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33769:18"/>
outward Service he ever perform'd to God. <hi>Pag.</hi> 141. <hi>H. C.</hi> Nay, and lays down that infamous as well as Treaſonable Principle; That if he had taken up Arms againſt the Parliament, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells him he had been a Traytor. A rare Chriſtian Conſcience, for a Preacher of Chriſt, and one that had taken the Oath of Allegiance, to declare it to be Treaſon to defend his Liege Lord. But this Gentleman was better read in <hi>Scripture</hi> than our <hi>Laws;</hi> and indeed one would think ſo, that ſhall ſee him urge all thoſe Texts of it, that were intended for lawful Governours, to preſs Obedience to the uſurped Powers; <hi>thoſe</hi> he ſaid, could not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed without damnation, but the King might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for Loyalty in this Man's Divinity, is the unpardonable Tranſgreſſion. For Rebellion againſt the King, he thinks, needs no Repentance, or no Mercy, and therefore, (ſays he) having ſearched into the matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> as to my concernment in the War, I am ſo far from Repenting, that I could not forbear doing the ſame, under the ſame circumſtances. And truly Cuſtom in this matter is a very fine thing, he that has practiſed ſo well againſt one Prince, can tell how the better to deal with another.</p>
            <p>And as to Princes in general, the late Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> that had ſo many Diſciples at his feet, has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, That when Kings command unrighteous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33769:19"/>
things, and their Subjects do obey them; no doubt but the deſtruction of them both is juſt, and righteous. And it is no doubt if theſe <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> could determine it as readily by the <hi>Sword,</hi> as with their <hi>Pens.</hi> And though indeed they have Hypocriſie, and Impudence, equal to their Wickedneſs, and would bear the World in hand; that they are Harmleſs and Innocent, yet from them it is that the Eaſie and the Zealous, are taught to deſie Government, and put in practice the worſt Principles of their Maſters. I need not inſtance in any more particulars, <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Beza, Knox</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> have taught the whole Herd of Diſſente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> such horrible things, that as they themſelves ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> manag'd them, have in all Nations prov'd to the continual diſturbance of the Peace, and to the Murder of a great many Princes, as does appear in Hiſtory. And indeed the firſt Man in Story, that ſpake evil of Kings, was a <hi>Separatiſt.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> tells us of <hi>Lucifer Caralitanus,</hi> who ſpoke hard things of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the <hi>Arrian Emperour;</hi> but the Father obſerves, that he was one that did Separate from Church-Communion. After that, the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and with them ſince have joyn'd the <hi>Presbitery,</hi> both the one and the other, having declined from <hi>Primitive Piety,</hi> fell off from their Loyalty alſo, and reckon it no Sin, to Curſe or Rebell againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33769:19"/>
their Prince. But in all the firſt times of Religion, for ſome hundreds of Years, the Chriſtians by their Books, and by their Bloud, gave Teſtimony that Kings are in no caſe to be Conſpired againſt or Reſiſted. Hence <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us for the honour of Chriſtianity, that when there was a Rebellion made againſt a Bloudy, and a Cruel <hi>Emperour,</hi> out of pretence for <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Publick-Good,</hi> the Chriſtians then would not be inſnared into Evil by the glorious Baits of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude, Chriſt never gave any other Rules than what are in the Text, <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> the one when the Prince commands as he ſhould, and the other when he commands what he ought not. And thus we either obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſuffering like Chriſtians, ſhall dye like ſuch, and He that calls us to Grace, will one day bring us to Glory, and Crown both our Doings and our Sufferings, with Peace and Glory, and Immortality.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
